[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Well, hello. Here we are. Here we go.
Welcome to the Ask Abijit Show, the
history episode today. I hope everyone's
doing great. Uh, good to see you all.
Let us see who all is there in the live
chat. I can see Aayush Singh, Aayush
Yadav, Yvra Singh, Shikh Havat, Manisha
Kardo, HB, Samana Satish,
Moonlight, Sonata from Mitilanchal.
Well, good to see you sir. Mystic SK,
Swami, Jane, Sun, Mr. Jam, Radhi, Radi,
Nal, Nesh, Nali, good evening. A Singh,
Sumit Agarwal, Negro, Shiva, Sai, Alka,
Shikari, Mr. Jam Abi Chandel 005 Sumit
Jade Si Permar
PK PKS Geopolitical Dub Good evening
Anonymous Scientist Bonjour Mwah Purohit
welcome
Rajat Duhan Mr.
from Ireland. Good day to you. Astad
Vivei, Hensy, Penguin, Sena, Suas,
Reddi, uh, Sri Ram, Chandra, Namaha,
Ram, Ram, G. Uh, who else do we have? We
have animals for laugh fields strong man
wakam wakam vikash pj net nizen Amisha
hack hack care uh shanks kushal bondadi
sumitwal
sharma says cyus the great knockknock
says hi Rasputin vitri Martinez Rita upg
echo hersi
ak akhat
Ark Akhat all right good to see you kan
gun 15 Hayes says J hind uh Sharma
Didd's son is here well good to see you
did Diddy's son Aadi Singh Smith is
there Bushan is there Nand Nandish
Vladimir Putin sir is here good to see
you sir who else uh Swami Jane from
Jaipur Gravity Kah arrow 14 Nandish
Gorish KB from Dublin good to see you
sir Love Travel Guru Akash K Saria Set V
S N Vikash Dhavi Sangeita Jala Namaste K
Tanish Shri Aditya Dashi Sonavan and
everybody else all right let's uh get
going Singh Shakawad is from Jaipur
freedom from outcome is from Canada
Tushar Kalborgi rational thinker
and everybody else okay is there a
problem with the screen someone's saying
there's an issue with the screen. Not
anymore. Not anymore. All right. Good.
We're good to go. Okay. Let's take
questions that you all have asked in the
comments. I've selected about 20 25
questions. I will take as many as as
possible over the next couple of hours.
So, let's go with the questions. Where
are the questions? What do we have?
Amisha says, "What's the difference
between AD, BC, and CE?" What's the
difference between AD, BC, and CE? So
these are the uh terms we use to
describe years, historical years. 22 AD,
3000 BC. Sometimes we use CE and BCE.
What is all this? What's it's it's kind
of confusing, isn't it? It's kind of
confusing. What does it all mean? So um
this is all Christian terminology.
Earlier in history, historically
uh in history books, etc., we used to
use the terms AD and BC.
These days we have CE and BCE. These two
terms essentially mean the same things.
So what is AD? AD means ano domini.
It's a Latin term and it's been
abbreviated to AD. Anodomini. It means
the year of our Lord. It's a Christian
term. So Mr. Jesus Christ is supposed to
have been born in the year one. Right?
The year 1 the world the history begins
with the birth of Jesus Christ according
to the western world view historically
it's been that way. So the year 1 is 1
AD one un ano domini one the year one of
our lord our lord and savior that sort
of thing. So that's a so what's bc then?
So BC is very simple it's before Christ.
So if you say something happened in 50
BC it means 50 years before the birth of
Mr. Christ. If it's 30,000 BC BC, it's
3,000 years before the birth birth
apparent alleged birth of Mr. Christ. So
that was the deal. Okay, AD and BC. Now
you will see that people use CE and BCE
which means the same thing. CE now means
it it means common era and BCE means
before common era. While 1 B 1 A 1 CE is
the same as 1 A, they have simply
repackaged the ADBC terminology into
CEBC terminology so that it doesn't
sound overtly Christian. Common era
before common era. What's the common
era? It's your Christian era. It it may
as well as well stand for the Christian
era and before the Christian era. So
that's ADBC and CEBC. Same thing
repackaged. Earlier it used to be AD and
BC. Now it is looked upon as kind of
obsolete and now they use the terms CE
and BCE. Exactly the same meaning. It's
the beginning of the Christian era.
Beginning the first year of the birth of
Mr. Christ. That's ADBC and uh CEC. All
right. Next question. The next question
is by Tjari.
Did the Satwahanas mark the first
political assertion of an Andra identity
within a wider panindia cultural
framework? How did the satwahana's use
of prait over Sanskrit influence early
vernacular political consciousness in
the dean? The satwahanas the satwahanas
are a fascinating dynasty a fascinating
empire. I'm not sure if they are
regarded as an empire or a kingdom but I
see them as an empire. They they ruled
over a pretty vast amount area of land
in in central India the Dean region
essentially right. So uh the
establishment of the Satwana Satwahana
dynasty is around is said to be around
somewhere in the 3rd century BC or BCE
like we just uh discussed right around
230 to 240 BC around that time. the the
founder was Simuka. Simuka was the
founder of this dynasty. He overthrew
the existing dynasty of the time in that
region, the Kva dynasty. So Simuka is
the founder of the Satwana dynasty.
Sometime in the second half in the in
the latter half of the 3rd century BC.
Now the Satwahana dynasty, what does it
mean? Satwahana,
it means seven vehicles essentially,
right? It's it's an illusion to these
seven
horses of Surya Dave, the sun god. If
you look at the way Surya Dave is
depicted in art and literature, he is
supposed to come on a chariot that's
drawn by seven horses, right? Seven
horses. So that's that's the symbolism
behind the name Satwahanas.
Now if you look at the matsipuran
it refers to the satwahanas as the
andras. So that's the origin of of the
term Andhra Pradesh which is essentially
the same region. So the satwana dynasty
was the first you could say the first
major empire in the deken region after
the withdrawal and decline of the moria
empire. The Shunga Empire did not ever
come south of the Vindias essentially.
So the Satwana dynasty it founded an
empire. It eventually became an empire
that was the first major empire in the
region after the withdrawal and and
decline and eventual dissolution of the
Morius. So the founder is Simuka. He
overthrew the Kva dynasty. And then
after Simoka his brother Krishna or
Kanha ruled and he expanded the the
empire eastward eastward towards eastern
India in the Dakan region right. U then
you have various kings who come and then
one of the major early kings is
Satkarnney the first. He is still in the
BC time. Okay 70 60 BC around that time.
uh he was uh uh probably the most
important early ruler of the Satwan
dynasty. He was called the king the lord
of Dakshinapat means the southern region
of the subcontinent and he expanded his
empire significantly. He conquered
western Malva. He conquered the Narmmata
valley. He extended his rule in the in
various directions. He then started
behaving like an emperor because he was
a conqueror. He started performing the
ashwame yagna the rajasuya yagna which
indicates imperial status. No no
ordinary king will do those things right
and he satkari the first is the king who
established pratishtan as the major
capital as the capital of the satwan
empire. Today it's called pitan. It's in
Maharashtra. Right? So that is the first
major king. And then there's the golden
age of the Satwan Empire which comes
with under the the the rule of the great
Gautabi Puttra Satakarni.
So he ruled in the 2nd century AD or 2nd
century CE. Uh his
remarkable achievements are documented
in the Nashik Prat
Prashasti inscription which was created
by his mother Gautabi Balashri. His
mother Gautam Balashri was apparently a
very formidable lady and Goautami Puttra
Satakarnney was named after his mother
not his father. He is called Gautami
Puttra Satakarnney. So it was not a
patrineal dynasty as such but they
honored their mothers by naming the sons
after the mothers. So Gautametra sat
satakarni was a major was the greatest
of the kings of this dynasty and it's
possible that may that he may have
defeated the the Mahakshhatra
king Nahapana.
So the Mahakshhat the the western
satraps as they're called in English
they were descendants of skithians who
ruled in western India from Gujarat from
Maharashtra uh from Sarashtra they
controlled India's trade with Rome a
very very prosperous kingdom they had
and they were very powerful and one of
the most powerful of the Mahakhatrapas
was in Nahapana
and we're not sure if Gautamudra
Satakarni was a contemporary of Napana
or not but we know that some of
Nahapana's coins have been discovered to
have been restruct struck by Goautame
Puttra Satakarnney. So maybe Goautamra
Sakarnney defeated Nahapana or maybe he
took over some territory that earlier
belonged to Nahapana and that's why he
restructs. But anyway he uh came into
conflict with the Mahakhatraas with the
western satraps and he expanded his
kingdom in that direction. Um
it is possible that may he may have
reached Saashtra as well in the
northwest. Um and Mahapan sorry
Gautamudra was was called Raj Raj king
of kings which essentially means emperor
right great man uh his queen's name was
Vashishti and his son was Vashishti
Puttra Pulawami Puluwami and and
Vashishti Puttra Puluwami the successor
of Gautra Putra Satakarnney he continued
the dynasty's expansion eastwards and he
was able to successfully maintain
control over the vast Satwana Empire and
then eventually you have more kings like
Hajjri, Satkarnney and so on and then
there's the inevitable decline and
fragmentation of the empire and uh by by
the middle of the 3rd century AD uh the
you know there are there's a succession
of weak rulers who are unable to manage
the vast size of the empire and that's
why the empire starts fragmenting you
know local uh governors start becoming
rulers that sort of thing and eventually
there are other uh uh kingdoms that
encroach upon the territory and you know
how it goes right so what about the
uh contributions
what's the legacy of the satanas right
so first of all they are known to have
supported
cultural traditions civilizational
traditions they performed various
various vic yajnas they also supported
both the dharma they constructed
magnificent Buddha Buddhist stupas
chaita chaitas kla
Carla in in Maharashtra I believe it's
very famous it's still there it's still
a tourist destination it's somewhat okay
maintained right and they patronized
various monasteries through you know
donations and whatnot right uh after
they they started controlling the
western part of India they began to
control the the the maritime trade
between India and and Rome and the Roman
Empire um and when it comes to language
they used both Sanskrit and prait in
their inscriptions and they did
patronize prait literature. Right? So uh
yeah they were very significant
historically and eventually as as all
empires go they had to decline and and
excuse me they had to decline and
fragment right u but uh they made
significant contributions to art to
culture to architecture to civilization
they developed a very sophisticated
administrative system they fought the
the western satrups and I think had good
success against them against them and
they represent kind of a bridge between
what you call south Indian and north
Indian traditions right uh so that was
the deal with the satwahana so did so is
this the first political assertion of an
andra identity within uh panindian wider
etc well they are called the andras in
yeah you know in in literature so yeah
you could say it's it's the beginning
you could say of the of the andra
identity and they did use prait as well
as suskrit but sanskrit was always the
civilization traditional language and
until very recently it was now it's been
jettisoned but anyway but they did use
they did patronize prait literature
uh so that isn't indeed the case so
prait is obviously uh an offshoot of
Sanskrit right and eventually the common
people would no longer speak Sanskrit
like they used to do in the vic times
and common people used to use speak a
variety of of aparential languages and
prait was one of them one of one of the
earlier ones Of course, one of the even
earlier ones was Pali. As we know,
during the Morian times, the local
people of Magad used to speak Pali.
Anyhow, so so that's the deal with the
Satwanas. Very important dynasty,
fascinating dynasty. Uh kind of
overlooked in Indian history. Nobody
kind of remembers them too too much. I'm
sure there is more consciousness about
the contributions and and the legacy and
the great achievements of the South
Vanas in the Dean region. Hopefully, I
hope so. And yeah, great dynasty. Great
question.
Right.
Real real Vladimir Putin says recently
BRI has claimed that Indians used gold
coins during the Harapan and Digvidic
times. This contradicts the fact the
fact the fact that Kushans brought gold
coins to India. What's my opinion?
I I did not know until now that Kushans
apparently brought gold coins to India.
Yeah. Did they? I mean everything of
value has to come from outside is it?
Well, the Kushans obviously eventually
became Indian. We they are they are
renowned for their gold coinage. No
question about that. But
but is it like I did not know that
people believe this that the Kushans
brought gold coins to India. Before that
India did not have gold, no coin. We did
not have the concept of gold coins or
anything. Right? We were absolute
simpletons. Is it so? So uh
let's uh let's try and pull something
up.
So let me show you something. I don't
know about the rigidic times because we
have no idea when the rigidic times
happened for sure the exact time period.
But look at this. Uh this is from
numista harapan primitive money from 3
to 1500 BC. This is gold.
Uh if it will ever open.
Apparently it will not. Let's try again.
Will you open up?
Maybe you will not. Maybe the website is
broken. Uh so anyway, this is Harrap and
primitive money as it is uh portrayed
over here. 3,00 to 2,500 BC Indust
Valley civilization. Gold disc possibly
earring. It does it doesn't look like
earring to me. I mean, if you try to
insert that into your ear over earlobes,
it will slice open your earlobes. So
clearly this is not ear rings. And look
at the precision. Ah, look at that. Look
at the precision with which it is cut.
It's almost industrial. It's almost like
it's been done by with a machine. That's
what it looks like. And this is gold, by
the way. Okay. This is gold. Uh, and you
find this sort of thing in the Mundy
Horde and whatnot. So, this is from 3000
BC. Um, so we don't have
the effigy of a king on this. We don't
have any inscriptions on this but
clearly this seems to be this I mean if
you are using gold this is not obviously
a weight of measure for if you want to
use weights and measures you would use
stones or or lead or tin or iron you
would not use something as precious as
gold. Gold was always precious
historically. So this looks like some
standardized you know currency without
any fe any any inscription or stamp or
any such thing or or markings of a king
or any uh any any text on it. So if you
look at the Harapan time per the Sindu
Saraswati time period of our history you
will find that there are no statues of
kings anywhere. You only find statues or
or descriptions or or seals of deities
and they seem to be really fond of rdra
Lord Shiva. So there's a lot of rdra
everywhere and there are various animals
that are depicted. There is the
pashupati depiction and so on but you
will not find any depiction of any king
over there anywhere. I'm sure they had
kings but it looks like they were also a
rather democratic society. I mean at
that time our ancestors because there
are I mean the ruins are extensive you
have metropololises from that time
there's no palaces or any such thing so
it looks like it was a very democratic
form of governance of some kind uh so
that's why they did not uh you know
have um inscriptions of kings so this is
clearly some form of currency from that
time harapan times or sarasati hindu
times Uh that's our ancient past like
30,000 BC maybe even before that it was
it must have been in in in form in in in
use in usage. So definitely you had I'm
just giving you one example. I'm sure if
you look you'll find more. We're just
doing a live show over here so there's
no time to go and look spend 20 minutes
looking for something but you'll find
it. So clearly during Harapan times you
did use gold currency not in the shape
and form of you know exalting and
glorifying emperors having having
inscriptions on top but it was clearly
standardized
and punched marked or whatever when it
comes to rigidic times I don't know see
first of all no one knows what the
rigidic era was how long ago was it we
don't know that there's a debate there's
a there's a battle there's a raging
battle going on between various experts
about the date of the Vic of the Riga
and the date of the Rama and the date of
the Maharat I don't want to get into
that it's it's a mess okay uh so we
don't know there are all kinds of dates
that have been proposed like 1500 BC
some people say you know the iron
invasion theorists some people say
12,000 13,000 BC all wide variety of
dates so we don't know what the rigidic
era was from the way I see it it was
closer to the time when the Saraspati
was still a mighty river compared to
when the Saraspati had dry half dried
out. So it's closer to 6,000 BC than to
1500 BC but that's a vast time period.
When was it? We don't know. So if we
don't know the time period then how do
we know what went on at the time and
what currency was being used whether
gold gold coins were being used or not.
So about rigidic rigidic times I can't
say but Harapan times or or Sarasati
Sarasati Hindu times we definitely had
gold currency not in the shape and form
that we are used to today. Maybe the way
we use it is more primitive than what we
our ancestors were were using during the
Saraswati Sindu times. That was more
standardized. It was just pure currency.
No markings of kings and no exaltations
through inscriptions of the kings and
their their great deeds or anything.
Just pure currency.
All right.
Nirvana Shanks says, "Everyone talks
about Rome. Rome. Rome. Rome. They talk
about the Mongols these days, land
empires. But no one talks about the
Phoenicians, the Carthaginians,
Shri Vijaya, the great maritime powers.
Uh they control trade. They maybe even
more than anyone else. Why do they get
so little credit? Uh thank you for your
attention to this question. Yes, I mean
see
the the world is very euroentric today.
Really euroentric. All our history is
written in in in a foreign language. I'm
speaking to you in a foreign language.
All the the the standardized textbooks
are written by westerners or people who
are culturally and intellectually
westernized. So they will see everything
from that perspective. And from the
western perspective, from the European
or accidental perspective, everything
centers around Rome because that was the
great empire that they produced.
Right? I mean if you look at the US, the
US is a dominant power today. It
controls the world's culture. It's got a
huge cultural influence on the world and
what they say is what everyone believes,
right? I mean in India, we did American
validation for our to feel good about
about ourselves. So if you look at the
Americans,
how what do they see as the the the
origins of their culture? If you see the
American Express credit card, what do
you see on that?
You see the a depiction of a Roman
centurion,
don't you? That's what you see. So they
also hearken back to Rome. So the the
west is obsessed with Rome and they talk
about Rome constantly. If you go on
social media, Rome, Rome, Rome,
nostalgia for Rome and so on cuz they
can't talk about a certain other empire.
So they'll talk about Rome. Uh Mongols,
no one talks about Mongols until I
started talking about it. Actually
before the year 2020, I you did not hear
anyone talking about the the Mongols.
Okay? The Mongols were demonized. They
were portrayed essentially as cannibals
of some kind.
and they they actually were depicted
historically as cannibals. No one spoke
about the Mongols until I spoke about
the Mongols actually. Uh there there
were a few books written here and there
but it never entered popular discourse
until kind of I spoke about. So I I will
take some credit for that. Uh but the
west is obsessed with Rome. Everything
came from Rome perhaps from Greece
because Greece is the spiritual uh
spiritual uh parent essentially and
cultural parent of Rome.
So they'll speak about Rome, they'll
speak about Greece and they take some
ideas from places like Egypt and and the
fertile crescent Mesopotamia and so on.
But they will never credit empires to
the to the east of what they call the
Middle East. They'll never credit any
cultures from the east. Uh so and and
when and also the Phoenicians
Carthaginian. So first of all who were
the Phoenicians? Who were the
Carthaginians? For that we must go to
map. So let me bring map on screen. Yes,
let us bring the map on the screen and I
will explain who the phoenetians who the
Carthaginians were and then we'll talk
about S Vijay as well. So
we recognize this part of the world.
Yes. Let's go westwards.
Let's go to the place which we now call
Israel.
So back in the day around around let's
say 1,000 BC or maybe around 800 BC this
region which is now called Israel
there used to live a Semitic people
there.
Those people were called the Phoenicians
and it so these people originated in
this region what is now Israel
and then they expanded westwards
in North Africa and they eventually
um you know
they eventually founded kingdoms and all
that in North Africa which eventually
would become Carthage and so on. So the
Carthaginians were the descendants of
the Phoenicians
and they were a maritime people. They
engaged in trade and they had kind of
good powerful powerful navies and all
that and Carthage eventually almost
ended up destroying Rome almost.
Hannibal Barka was the guy who almost
succeeded in that. Uh so the Europeans
do speak about Carthage and the
Phoenicians.
Then let's talk about uh Sri Vijaya. So
Sh Vijaya is an empire that emerged in
Sumatra. Sumatra is the western most the
western large island of Indonesia.
Um and the Shri Vijaya was obviously a
Hindu Hindu kingdom and yeah it was a it
was a pretty pretty powerful kingdom
very culturally and civilizationally
very rich very similar to India and its
successor one of its successors
eventually was the Majapahit Empire
which was the greatest empire in the
history of of Indonesia. It was what we
call athalasoccratic empire, a maritime
empire and they were pretty strong,
pretty powerful in the entire region
over here. And Shiva obviously was was
defeated by the Chas. The Chas the Chola
Empire invaded Shivija and defeated them
and and turned the entire region into
the into the Chola. And since we are
talking about various empires that are
kind of disregarded, let's talk about
the Champa Empire. Champa Kingdom which
was in power for a very very long time.
It ruled out of what is essentially
southern Vietnam. It was again a Hindu
kingdom or empire. Again a taloscratic
or maritime empire. And this entire
region was dominated by the navy of the
Champa kingdom. Champa the so-called
South China Sea should be called the
Champa Sea because the Chinese never had
any navy in the region. They never had
any influence in the region. So that's
the deal. There are so many such
disregarded kingdoms and empires who
have contributed so much historically
and whose legacies still live on in
various shapes and forms. But if you ask
the west, it's all Rome, Rome, Rome,
Rome, Rome. That's the that's the way
things go, right? You see things from
your perspective. That's why other
kingdoms, empires, and cultures and
civilizations get so little credit.
That's just the way things go. Okay,
what do we have next?
Aayush Singh says tell us about why
Japan has helped tell us about why Japan
agreed to help in li liberating India
through the Azad Hind force and why
didn't the Nazis agree to liberate India
well you see Shri Subash Chandraos did
initially
uh journey so he was under house arrest
in India wasn't he and then he escaped
from house arrest test. He escaped to he
traveled a long journey in disguise. He
went to northwest India. He went to
Kabul. Through there he went into
central Asia and he eventually made his
way to Germany.
And he met with the top leadership of
the Third Reich. He let he met with
Adolf Hitler and he said that our enemy
our common enemy is the British, the
godamn British. So let's work together.
Please help me to liberate India. So
Adolf fitler at the time was well he had
plans of world conquest and world
domination and he had allies in the east
which is Japan. So he said to subashadra
look I am over here all the way west in
Europe. India is so far away uh I am
right now uh you know focusing on other
things. I will not have uh time or
resources or manpower to to spare
in a project that would be the
liberation of India from the godamned
British. So he said let me put in a word
with my allies in Japan. Okay, I'll give
you I recommend that you go and go to
Japan and talk to them and they will be
in a better position to help India out.
So then Subbashandra Bose went all the
way from Germany all the way to Japan
essentially the other side of the world.
He spent some of some part of the
journey in a submarine and so on.
Eventually went to Japan and once again
he was able to I mean he was he was that
kind of person that you know he was a
doors would open for him. So he went and
he met with the Japanese top leadership
and the Japanese leadership said all
right we will assist you which are we
have
many Indian prisoners of war who are
fighting for the British we will hand
them over to you. You create a force out
of that and the objective should be to
liberate India and we will assist you in
that. So look what was the Japanese
calculations? The Japanese calculations
were the complete conquest of Asia. They
wanted to conquer the whole of Asia. At
one point in time they were knocking on
India's doorstep. There were battles in
India's far east. Battle of Himfal,
battle of Kohima, right? And some of the
combatants were Azadhind Azadhind Hind
force Azad Hind forge soldiers.
So the Japanese they also had conquered
the Andaman islands and they were pretty
brutal there. So the Japanese actually
wanted to conquer India and vasalize
India. If they had conquered India, they
would not most likely have let India go.
they would have uh well they would have
occupied India the same way the British
did. Now let's understand one thing.
Subashandra Bose was smarter than you
and me. He was more intelligent than us.
He understood full well what the
Japanese want. But that's how it goes.
Sometimes you know what they want and
what they want isn't good. But the
common enemy is more dangerous and and
more immediate. So let's take help from
the Japanese. Let's see. Even though I
know that they actually want to occupy
India, but maybe once I once things go
right, maybe I can ward of the Japanese
as well. Maybe that was a calculation.
So uh that's why the Japanese agreed to
help because they were much closer to
India. They had already conquered many
parts of Asia. Well, you know,
eventually they reached Burma and and
the far east of India. So they were not
far. The Germans were far away. They
were nowhere. their forces, their power
projection, it was nowhere close to
India. The Japanese, they were on
essentially on the doorstep of India
eventually. So that's why the Japanese
it was it was more practical for them to
help Subashandra in the in the
liberation of India. The Nazis could not
do that. So that's that's how it went.
Sam Brahmanik says, "Can you please
explain which event was the official
declaration that Britain is no longer a
superpower?" Well, there's no uh
official declaration as such, but uh I I
understand what you're asking. So, it
happened in stages.
The the second world war Britain was
isolated. The whole of Europe had fallen
to the third Reich. France had fallen.
You had the you had the Vichi regime in
France. the puppet regime which was
actually a Nazi puppet regime
and the rest of Europe had fallen to the
Nazis and there was the battle of
Britain. The Nazis were trying to hammer
Britain into the dust.
So Britain was under siege
and without American help they would
have gone under. And of course American
help isn't free. The Americans loaned
whatever they did to Britain and Britain
had to repay that. And Britain was
repaying the debt to the Americans until
the beginning of the 21st century, this
century until not so long ago. That's
how much debt the British owed the
Americans. So the Americans uh whatever
help they offered, they offered it at a
price. So that itself was complete
humiliation of the British. What
imperial status? There was no imperial
status once that happens. So that you
could say was the you could say
unofficial death snell of the British
Empire. The British Empire was no longer
a superpower. It was no longer an
empire. It was just an island under
siege. That's what Hitler had reduced
reduced Britain to. And the Americans
magnanimously helped Britain out. So
Britain essentially was in a subsidiary
position. Simple as simple as that. But
if you want a real official I mean
declaration to the world that hey it's
over for you guys to it's over for the
British. The days of empire are over.
Well, for that you would have to go back
go back to 1956.
1956 the Suis crisis. Let's go to the
map once again.
The Sue crisis. Sue. So where is Sue?
Let's go west of India
and let's go to Egypt. So when you go to
Egypt, you will see the that between the
Red Sea and the Mediterranean Sea,
there's this piece of land which
connects Africa with Asia. But if you
look closer, there is a canal which
starts from Suis also.
And there's this great bitter lake here,
this Timsah lake. And if you go further
north, you reach port say where the
canal opens up into the Mediterranean
Sea. This is the Suez Canal. And the
British essentially were major
stakeholders in the Suez Canal. There
was a point in time when the Suez Canal
was called uh the spinal cord
essentially of the British Empire
because it is what enabled the British
to reach India fast because India was
their major possession during colonial
times and even after the second world
war the British were major stakeholders
in the Suez Canal and so were the
French. So the British and the French
were major stakeholders in the Suez
Canal. Okay. Now what happens uh what
happens now is that
somewhere in the 1950s probably around
uh Nasser
who was the ruler of Egypt he decided to
nationalize the Suez Canal. What does it
mean that it was nationalized? It means
that the government of Egypt bought out
the shares. It did not simply confiscate
the Suez Canal and take it by force. It
paid the shareholders whatever they were
owed and took control of the Sewish
Canal. So the British and the French
lost control of the Sewish Canal. The
Suez Canal became entirely controlled by
the Egyptian government and in response
to that the British and the French they
launched they they hatched a conspiracy
together. They uh launched a maritime
invasion of Egypt and they landed in
Port Sai and took control of Port Sai.
This happened probably in October or
somewhere around that time 1956
and the USSR which was on good terms
with Egypt. It protested. The Americans
also protested and then the Americans
took the French and the British to task
not militarily but diplomatically. Okay.
They took the French and and the British
to the diplomatic negotiating table.
Twisted their arms until the arms were
all the way around like that. arm
twisted the British and the French and
within a few days by December or some
something around that time the British
and the French withdrew from Port Sed
and the attempt to take Sues was over.
That was humiliation. It was a public
slap in the face of both the British and
the French. So that was unambiguous
assertion to the entire world that
Britain is now a second rate world
power. It's forget about being a
superpower and an empire. It's not even
a first rate world power. It's now well
not it wasn't a vasal of the US at the
time but it was humiliated by the US and
the French were too. And let's not
forget Israel's Israel's uh role in
this. So the invasion
was a joint invasion not just by the
British and the French but also by
Israel. So British, French and Israeli
troops invaded
and the Israelis were persuaded by the
by the Americans to uh withdraw and the
British and the French were arm twisted
into withdrawing. So that you could say
was the well that was the day that the
world understood that Britain the
imperial days are are are long gone and
Britain is now not even a first rate
world power. It's a second great world
power. And once uh Tony Blair came to
power, it became a US poodle, the US
masal. And that's when it became a third
rate world power.
Right.
Yajnavalia says
Gayat Vincent has written an article or
a book. It's a book. The beef taboo in
China agriculture ethics sacrifice.
Honolulu University of Hawaii Press
2025. This year it's come out. So this
book claims that there was a strong beef
taboo in preodern China. So can we say
that Hindus have preserved their food
taboss better than the Hanchinese?
Let's Google this. Okay, let's let's
Google this and find out together what
this is all about.
So Google the beef taboo in China
agricult Oh, there we have it.
The beef taboo in China, agriculture,
ethics sacrifice. Let's go to uh this
here. Let's see what the book is about.
So, let's read this. The beef taboo in
China explains how and why. Around the
turn of the second millennium, which is
around 1000 AD, the Chinese determined
that cattle should not be slaughtered or
eaten. This taboo remained prevalent
until the beginning of the 20th century
and it is still observed by some today.
So, it lasted a thousand years. It was
prevalent until the beginning of the
1900s.
And the author situates this prohibition
with an evolving Chinese attitude
towards animals and meat and juxtaposes
the taboo with vegetarianism.
Hello.
All right, I am back. Sorry about that.
Am I audible now?
Just let me know once I I get your
I get your feedback I will resume. Ah
yes it is okay now. Okay apologies for
that. I have no idea what went wrong but
here we are. I've got a different mic
over here and we can uh continue with
what we are discussing. So we were
talking about the beef taboo in China
agriculture ethics and so on. So let me
resume uh answering. So we have this
book that's come out this year and uh
let's see the book all over again. So
this is the book and it says so this is
by uh Vincent Gossert and Barbara
Ambrose.
The beef taboo in China agriculture
ethics and sacrifice.
So what does the book description say?
The beef taboo in China explains how and
why around the turn of the second
millennium the Chinese deter the turn of
the second millennium means around a
thousand years before today. Okay. So
around the turn of the second millennium
the Chinese determined that cattle
should not be slaughtered or eaten. This
taboo remained prevalent until the
beginning of the 20th century and it is
still observed by some Chinese people
today. which means that until the early
1900s they still had the beef taboo. Uh
Gosset situates this prohibition within
evolving Chinese attitudes towards
animals and meat. And he juxtaposes the
taboo with vegetarianism and other other
forms of meat ethics. He argues the
emergence of this specific practice must
be understood in several contexts.
Notably, a new agricultural economy and
ecology in early modern times that
protected plow cattle and marginalized
pastures. Sacrificial reform that
eliminated beef as the standard offering
to gods and spirits. The development of
Dowist rituals, cults and moral
theology, the taboo beef and made this
observance a lynch pin of Chinese
civilization. It's very interesting that
this author I mean I've not seen the
book. It looks like there is no mention
of the Indian influence in China because
China was majorly Buddhist for a long
long period of time. Even today, China
is China has the world's largest
population of practicing Buddhists.
It's interesting that this uh book
doesn't mention the Buddhist or in
Indian influence at all. Right.
Um
yeah. So anyway, so it's clear that for
for a thousand years, eating beef was a
taboo in China. Now, let me show you
something else. Let me show you a
different
story. Okay, let's go to Google and
let's talk about Japan.
Okay.
Was beef
taboo for the
samurai?
Was beef? Yes. Beef consumption was
taboo for samurai and for the general
population of Japan for a significant
period due to religious, Buddhist and
practical reasons. A ban on eating
cattle was first imposed in 675 AD and
was strictly enforced until the Maji
restoration until the 19th century.
1,500 years the Japanese did not eat
beef
and the emperor Maji himself consumed
beef to modernize the country. Look at
what was done to Japan. Exactly what you
seeing in India today. Eating beef is a
sign of modernity.
Yeah. Modernity.
So the Maji emperor, the guy who
attempted to eradicate dharma from
Japan, he's the guy who ended the
prohibition on on beef. And because he
consumed beef and he's the divine
emperor, that's why everybody was
encouraged to start eating beef. And
today Japanese the Japanese people most
of them they eat beef but for about 1500
years almost the Japanese would not
touch beef. The samurai the samurai the
great warriors do you know what their
diet was?
Samurai.
Yes. Samurai diet. There you go. What
did they eat? They would eat fish. Yes.
But they would not eat any other meat.
Primarily plant-based. Mostly
vegetarian. They would have rice, miso
soup, pickled vegetables, seafood and
seasonal fruits. They would eat fish. So
the samurai were like the Bengales. You
see the Bengali people, most Bengales
who eat fish do consider themselves
vegetarian.
Fish is the fruit of the sea apparently.
So the samurai, the samurai diet was
primarily vegetarian. They would eat
fish and seafood, not no red meat,
definitely no beef. So whether you look
at China, whether you look at Japan,
there was a complete taboo on beef. The
Japanese were and the Japanese civilians
were mostly vegetarian for the longest
time. Let's look up that also. Uh Japan
veget
historical
vegetarian history. Let's look at that
history of meat cons. Japan's history
with vegetarianism is rooted in Buddhist
consumption uh influence a period of
restricted meat consumption from 675 CE
until 1872.
So the whole of Japan was like that not
just the samurai.
They would eat fish but apart from that
it was mostly
mostly vegetarian food. No red meat, no
no birds, no livestock.
This is all Indian influence. all Indian
influence and today let's let's look at
India today
eating beef is is a sign of being modern
I have nothing against protein
eat protein yeah sure absolutely you
need s sufficient protein and I would
encourage all Indians to consume
sufficient protein
especially if you I mean especially men
yeah you got to bulk up a little bit you
can't be little skinny little voses yeah
But beef, why beef?
Why beef? People are being encouraged to
eat beef in India. So anyhow, even
today, most Indians, most Hindus at
least, most most they don't eat beef.
And thank the gods for that. So yes, you
could say Hindus until now have kind of
preserved their food tabos better than
the Hanchinese and better better than
the Japanese. Sad to see what's happened
to those cultures. They've been
destroyed. Yeah. Okay.
Anonymous scientist says 3,000-year-old
Syrian hymn found in Ugarit, Syria
matches riga melodies according to US
archaeology magazine. What's my
comments? So understand what's melody?
What's melody?
So this news doesn't seem to say that
it's rigidic
the the language of the rigida vic. It's
not saying that it is Vic Sanskrit. The
hymn is in the huran language but the
melody is rigidi. What does it mean? The
meter the meter
the meter of the verse
is it matches the rigid exactly. So
let's look look this up here. Harapan
um okay let's go to archaeology news and
look up what the article has to say.
Okay, so 3,000-y old hymn reveals
musical links across Bronze Age
civilizations from India to the
Mediterranean. Let's read it briefly.
More than 3,000 years ago, in the port
city of Ugarit on the eastern coast of
the Mediterranean, the scribes inscribed
a song in the Hurian language on a clay
tablet. The hymn to Nikal is the
earliest known musical score found to
date. Oh, it's a musical score with
melody and and okay, but notes. I
suppose if you are talking about a
score, you're talking about notes,
musical notes like sarabita, that sort
of thing. A recent study suggests that
this brief composition could be of
unprecedented importance. Evidence of a
share the global musical culture in the
bronze age. Let's find out what it is.
This study conducted by the University
of California, Santa Barbara's Dan
Cbachu and published on the preprint.org
org server compares the hymn to Nikal
with the rig va one of the oldest Indian
sacred no it's the oldest sacred it's
the oldest literature in the world
anyhow using computerass assisted rhythm
and melody mapping Bachu's study
demonstrated astonishing parallels
between the two pieces between the
rigida and this hymn to Nikal Bachu
explained that one in five rigveda
verses ends with the same cadence as the
the hymn to Nikal the odds of this
occurring ing by accident are less than
one in a million.
Okay. U so what astonished researchers
is not only the shared rhythm but also
the echoed melodic tendencies.
Let's let's read this first. Cadences
repeated melodic or rhythmic units act
as musical punctuation marking verse
endings. Two cadences dominate in the
hymn to Nikal. One simple and one
heartbeat. One simple and heartbeat like
and one is more intricate. These same
two models are used in the Rigveda with
one most frequently used ending verses
and the other linked closely to the
thristub meter. According to Bachu, this
duality of the simple and the complex,
he argues, is a more del is a deliberate
artistic choice. What astonished
researchers is not only the shared
rhythm but also the echoed melodic
tendencies. Ancient commentators on the
Rigveda described its melodies as
mounting upon accented syllables and
falling thereafter. A structure also
found in the Ugarthic hymn. When
reconstructed digitally, the two pieces
resonated with such similar
characteristics that their kinship
became unmistakable.
This discovery opens questions about the
ways in which music was spread across
long distances in ancient times.
Situated at at the crossroads of near
eastern and Mediterranean trade, Ugarit
connected Mesopotamia and Anatolian
cultures. The Mitani Kingdom is referred
to by historians as a probable bridge
between Ugarit and India. The Hurian
occupied Bronze Age state linked with
Indo-Uropean speaking communities would
have been the channel through which Vic
traditions and musical forms were
exchanged. Okay,
we understand what they're trying to
say. Incredible similarities. Impossible
to be an accident right 3,000 years ago
Ugarit
now at that time. So first of all let's
go let's find out where is Ugarit shall
we? Let's find out where is Ugarit.
Let's go to our friend Google
and let's ask Google where is Ugarit.
Uh not here. So sorry
where is Google? Here is Google.
Ugarit
map location
Ugarit. Where is it? Uh if you go to
images,
you will find that.
Okay, it's it's somewhere over here. All
right, we get it. It's uh north of
Lebanon. Uh if we go to the map, let's
go to the map now. I found the location
and we will put that on the screen.
Excuse me.
So let's zoom into the place
somewhere here.
So in in present day Turkey, but this
was a region that was part of the Mitani
Empire about let's say 1,400 years ago.
But this hymn is about from about 1,000
BC, not from 1400 BC. And by the time
the Mitani Empire no longer existed. Now
why do I talk about the Mitani Empire?
Because the Mitani Empire's rulers were
Indo-aranian like they say they spoke
Sanskrit but but late Vic Sanskrit not
rigidic Sanskrit they spoke late Vic
Sanskrit. Their kings had names like
thwarata and uh yeah all all Indian
names all Sanskrit names.
Um
so the the aristocracy of the Mitani
empire the royalty was Indians the local
people they all spoke the huran language
and after the empire dissolved I suppose
the royalty and the commerce must have
mixed up and the the high culture must
have survived for some time which is why
the huran hymn
it matches the melodies of the riga
so it's not that there was some mystical
connection between this region and India
uh the the fact is very clear I mean
it's very clear why it's so why why this
discovery has been made and what it
indicates it indicates that Indian
culture still lingered on for for some
time for some centuries after the
dissolution of the Mitani Empire the
Mitani rulers were Indian and some of
them they intermarried with the Egyptian
royalty
um yeah
that's my thoughts okay next
Amisha says in What way did the indust
valley civilization in influence Indian
civilization today? So when we say so
there is this big gigantic monstrous
gargantuan misconception that the indis
valley civilization was something that
happened in the past. Yeah it did happen
in the past but it's something that
disappeared. The indis valley
civilization people believe disappeared
and no one knows what happened to it. It
simply vanished. What happened to those
people? What was their culture? What was
the language? That's what people believe
because that's what you taught in your
textbooks and that's what your teachers
tell you. The it was first of all it was
not the Indispelli civilization. It was
the the the major river of the
civilization was the Saraspati. Okay.
The Sindu was a secondary river and it
was actually a STAindui civilization or
Sarasati Sindu civilization whatever you
want to call it but it did not simply
vanish.
It still exists.
We are the continuation of the of of
that time. Those were our ancestors.
They did not ever vanish anywhere. The
cities were abandoned because when you
are built, see in the old days, cities
were always built on the banks of rivers
and when a river disappears, what do you
do? You need to move somewhere else. And
of course, there are droughts and all
that which which causes climate change
and you need to move because of that.
So, it did not the cities were never
were not abandoned overnight. People
gradually moved away to other parts of
the subcontinent. Some moved westwards.
So the civilization never disappeared.
It continued in different shapes and
forms. We are the continuation of of the
civilization.
People say but their language hasn't
been deciphered. How do we know what
they wrote and what is the connection?
The language has been deciphered.
Baratra has deciphered it. You can see
the podcast on my channel on this
channel. He has deciphered it
and what does it turn out to be Sanskrit
and you can see his website um I think
it's called indescript.com if I'm not
mistaken you will see the entire
decipherment of the entire corpus of
Harapan texts Harapan indust valley
whatever you want to call them texts the
the inscriptions all of them all of them
have been deciphered
it was Sanskrit I mean what else do you
want some people won't believe it some
people because they don't want to
believe it they will not believe it I
Don't blame them for not believing it.
Once you have certain ideas in your
mind, for most people, it's impossible
to remove them. Once you are emotionally
attached to some ideas, you're stuck
there. If it's only through a great
amount of effort that you can keep
learning and and be open
to considering seriously something that
you never believed was true or you
always believed was false, but that's
the only way you grow in life. Most
people after a certain age stop growing
and some people stop growing at the age
of 12. It looks like uh anyhow so if you
look at the various characterist now why
do I say that the civilization never
disappeared
it still exists well let me show you um
let's once again go to our friend Google
and let me show you why there's an
article from 2016 and 2017 it's called
the Arian invasion myth
myth by whom by somebody called Chavda.
So if you go to medium for example
you'll see this the Arian invision myth
of 21st century science debunks 19th
century Indology uh this is an article
written by me which year was this 2017
um now let me show okay look at this you
see these figurines these little figures
yes so you will see if if you zoom in if
you zoom And I'm sorry that's been
that's too far imbiganed bigified. But
if you look at these figures,
see their their hair. See the parting of
the hair. What do you see there? Can you
see where my mouse pointer is? Can you
see what color that is? That's red.
That's something that married ladies
uh that sindur which they use in their
head in the parting of their hair. Well,
that these these statueets are from
2,800 BC. They were found in
Baluchasthan. This is obviously the the
u the golden era, the golden age of the
so-called Indis Valley civilization,
right? The the mature Harapan age
supposedly.
So, you can see this is an example of
something people still do. It was being
done almost 5,000 years ago. Yeah,
almost 5,000 years ago. Uh so I'll tell
you what
um in the book the rigidic people
invaders immigrants etc. Professor
Bibilal gives extensive archaeological
evidence that many of the traditions and
customs prevalent in the Sindu Sarasati
civilization continue to exist in modern
India. Yoga
I mean there are statues of people doing
yoga from 3000 BC from what you call the
Saras the Indas Valley civilization the
Haratan civilization. Well we still do
yoga don't we?
The shivalinga in yoni I mean people
still worship that today don't don't
they the use of sindur in married
women's hair partition well people still
do that the used use of spiraled bangles
among women in hana and Rajasthan and
even Gujarat the folktale of the thirsty
crow well people still teach that that
folktale to their children uh the
namaste greeting well it you will see
lots of statues little statues of of
people doing namaste from this period of
time 3000 BC or even even older
Lord Shiva's trident. Well, you will
find lots of seals with the trident of
of Lord Shiva. Uh Shivalingers and so
much more. So much more. There are so
many aspects
of the culture of that lost civilization
that we still practice today.
So it did not influence our civilization
today. Our civilization today is a
continuation of that civilization. We
are the same civilization. The
civilization never ended. And that is
something people are not taught in
school or college or wherever. It's like
it was some some civilization that came
from the from god knows where and
disappeared god knows where. That's what
you're taught. Which is so wrong.
All right.
Yajjulka says, "Where did the last
common ancestor of homo sapiens
who also likely spoke language like us?"
Okay. and Dennis originate and live. Can
it be the Indian subcontinent? Oldest
fossils of neonals were found in Europe.
Oldest fossils of homo sapiens in
Africa. Oldest fossils of Denisovans in
Tibet, East Asia, Southeast Asia.
Okay.
So the Neanderthalss are believed. So
see they are they used to be our
cousins. The Neanderthalss. Uh they were
a human subspecies which means that you
could inter humans could interbreed with
them and produce viable offspring.
And indeed it is believed it is not
believed it is known that non-African
humans carry on average about 4%
Neanderal DNA and the lowest incidence
of neanderal DNA is in India. Apparently
our ancestors did not ever intermix with
Neanderthalss but the ancestors of the
Europeans and West Asians etc. they pos
they probably did. Okay, whatever. Uh so
the neonthals most likely uh emerged out
of Africa
and uh populated Europe and West Asia
probably not India as far as I know
there's no evidence of Neanderthalss in
India for whatever reason in the Indian
subcontinent. So u the Neanderthals most
likely their migration out of Africa
happened around 700 or 800,000 years
before today and they are our they were
our close relatives but they no longer
exist as a separate subspecies. how they
their DNA is is in homo sapiens itself.
So their descendants are among us but
they share very little traits of the
original Neanderthals. Um language they
probably spoke a language. Yeah, maybe
multiple languages. Dennis, we don't
know much about them. I mean I remember
it was I don't know 10 15 years ago when
the news came out that there's a new
human subspecies that has been
discovered a fragment of a of a of a
finger bone somewhere in Tibet or or no
the Denisova cave somewhere in Asiatic
Russia.
And then uh more fossils were discovered
in Tibet and wherever else. So the first
place was the Denisova cave in in
Russia. That's why they are called the
Denisoans. It doesn't mean that they
call themselves the Denisoans. Uh very
little is known about them. Their their
genetic traces are found in various
human populations. U but uh when what
was their origin? I'm not really sure
about that. I'm not sure anyone knows
what their origin was. Uh what we know
is that humanity seems to have
originated and emerged out of Africa.
Uh most likely the Neanderthalss
immigrated out of Africa about 700 or
8,000 years ago, 800,000 years ago.
Humans, us homo sapiens, we most likely
emerged out of Africa about between 80
and 70,000 years before today. Around
that time, maybe 85 perhaps. We're not
sure. Uh because we do find evidence of
homo sapiens in India.
um which seems to have and and we
there's a settlement somewhere that was
discovered in India about 80,000 years
old or something homo sapiens and that
settlement had survived the catastrophic
Toba super volcano explosion that
happened about 80,000 years ago so
clearly the migration happened most
likely before 80,000 years
so if Homo sapiens came out of Africa
80,000 years ago let's say or 85 but the
Neanderthals came out of Africa 700,000
years ago and Dennis we don't know what
when then it means that the last common
ancestor of the three subspecies would
have lived in Africa
uh to the best of the knowledge that we
have as of today our deep ancestry comes
from Africa that's the best of the
knowledge with new if new evidence is
found which points in some other
direction obviously we have to change
our mind but today the data says it's
Africa
So yeah that's what I can say.
Next question is by Rahul Dunak.
Why was there megapona?
Why did the megapona go extinct after
one after 10,000 BC? Uh was the
emergence of homo sapiens? One of the
reasons along with scarcity of food.
Okay. Why did the great megapona go
extinct somewhere around 10,000 BC? Did
it have something to do with the
emergence of humans, homo sapiens? Or
was there uh climate reason? Was there
scarcity of food? What was it? Okay,
first of all, we have to ask ourselves
what is megapona?
What is that? What is megapona? Megapona
means gigantic animals, huge.
Now if you think about it, we have
megapona today. What is an elephant? An
elephant is a gigantic piece of
equipment, isn't it?
Isn't it? It's a huge unit. It's a
megapona. Elephant. Giraffe. Giraffe is
megapona. Gigantic animal, right? What
else do we have other megapona today? We
have ostriches which are kind of
gigantic birds almost like dinosaurs.
There is that.
uh we have huge whales but when we talk
about megapona we talk about land
dwelling animals so we have some
megapona like the elephant like the
giraffe I don't know if you could call
the hippopotamus or something megapona
but you know elephant is there giraffe
is there um but when we talk about the
extinct megaphone now we talking about
animals like the megthereum
and u
stegoon or something it was called the
let's let's Google it quickly okay
examples of megapona
First of all, let me tell you what is
the megalodon. Me? No, meggathereum.
Mega, not the megalodon.
Meggatheium.
This was a gigantic sloth.
Okay. That lived in South America
through the end of the late pletoine.
The pletoine the late late pletoine. It
ends around 11,000 or 10,000 years
10,000 BC
around that time. So, Meggathereum was
this gigantic sloth. If you compare it
to the size of a human, you can see it
is huge, gigantic.
And they have found examples of bones of
megthereum that show clear sign of of
cutting by humans. So humans used to
hunt these beasts. They even found
megalodons trapped in caves and all. So
it looks like humans may have hunted
these beasts to extinction. What other
megapona do we have?
We had s we had saber-tooth cats. We had
these gigantic um we had obviously
masttodons and and mammoths
huge bisons. We had uh you had cave
bears. You had dire wolves. You had uh
other other species of gigantic uh
elephants, paraserium, whatever it is,
woolly rhinosaurus.
So many of these animals lived in South
America but many of them lived in
Eurasia as well like the mammoths and so
on and many of these go extinct around
10,000 BC. What was it? So around that
time you have the end of the last ice
age and the world starts warming.
Climate change. Okay. So climate change
happens and climate change unleashes the
deadliest predator of all homo sapiens.
Homo sapiens is the ultimate p predator.
Weak apes but frightfully intelligent
and they use tools. And who is their
ally? Their ally is the wolf or the dog.
So homo sapiens and and the dog they
form an alliance and they hunt everybody
all the animals. Uh so no matter how big
the animal is once you put your mind to
it your homo sapiens you can hunt it. So
mammoths go extinct around 10,000 BC.
Megthereum goes extinct around 10,000
BC. And these gigantic mammals, many of
these and mammals were grass-eing
mammals. And maybe some climate change
phenomenon must have made grass cars.
And if you are so large, if you are the
the size of a one-story or twotory
building, you need to consume a lot of
food. If you are a warm-blooded animal,
a mammal, and if there's a scarcity of
food, you you start dying off. So I
think it was a combination of of u human
hunting and possible food scarcity maybe
climate change that killed off many of
these gigantic animals. When you are a
huge animal it's very difficult for you
to survive to sustain uh to sustain
yourself to to find enough food to eat.
So that's why many of the megapona
disappeared. I'll tell you what,
there used to be hippopotami in India
about I don't know several thousand
years ago. We we find hippopotamus bones
in India.
Uh how long ago was that? Let's let's
find out. Yeah, good question. When did
the hippopotamus go extinct? When did
Indian hippo go extinct?
When did hippos go extinct in India?
About
some say 9,000 years ago, some say
16,000 years ago. So that also is kind
of the late pristine period. Not far
away from 10,000 BC, right?
What about ostriches? I think that would
be 30,000 years ago. Did you know that
we had ostriches in India? You find
ostrich shells in India. Ostriches
go extinct in India.
So that's 25 to 40,000 years ago. Okay.
So that's not the late Yeah. kind of
late plestoin but not the exact tail end
of the pletoine era. So ostriches went
extinct from India about 25 or so
thousand years ago. U hippos went
extinct about 10,000 years ago maybe
15,000 years ago. So hippos are
definitely kind of megapona and among
the birds ostriches are megapona. So we
had that in India as well. And u in the
Himalayas you used to have this gigantic
bears. You also had huge apes. Maybe we
still do. I don't know. We'll see about
that. The Yeti. So yeah, it was a
combination of factors. And I'm sure the
human factor also played a significant
role in the extinction of these giant
animals. So many of the megapona that
the world knows of are found in the
Americas because that's where most of
the research happens, right?
Um
and yeah once the once the ice melted so
the question then arises that when did
humans arrive in the Americas? The
classical answer is about 11,000 years
ago with the melting of the before
11,000 years ago. As long as the
illusion the bearing straight bridge was
still there, the ice bridge. Uh but most
likely that's not true. Most likely
humans arrived long before that. That's
a whole different controversy. We'll not
go into that. So that's the deal with
the megaphone.
Okay, next question is by nationalist
8850.
Who were the Kelts? Is it Selts? Is it
Kelts? I call them Kelts also. Who were
the Goths? Who were the Tutons? Who were
the Normans? Who were the Franks? Who
were the Britons? And who were the
Anglo-Saxons? And who was the rest of
the world?
These names are frequently used in
history, but it's all very confusing. I
understand. Of course, it's very
confusing. If you're not if you if
you're not taught this, if you then
it'll be confusing. It's it's it's such
a multitude of names. Okay,
where do I begin? Kelts, Gothans,
Normans, Franks, Britons. Let's talk
about the Kelts and the Breton first.
The Celtic peoples, well, they still
exist. So, the Celtic people, they lived
in Western Europe, Western Europe. So if
you think about
imagine Stonehenge,
the Kelts did not build Stonehenge. What
is Stonehenge? Let let's let's find out.
Okay, Stonehenge.
It's this monument in in England.
This monument here, very famous.
Yeah. Because it's in England and and
they put it all over the postcards and
the internet. That's why it's very
famous. This monument is called
Stonehenge.
This was built how long ago? Several
thousand years ago. Uh what's the early
history?
Uh place of burial from its beginning to
the zenith and third millennium BC or
whenever before the monument Stonehenge
about 3,000 BC was built. Okay. The
point is that Stonehenge was not built
by the ancestors of today's British
people at least the male ancestors.
Uh
it was the original British people who
built Stonehenge and then there was a
genocide in the British Isles. What
genocide? Well, a bunch of barbarians
invaded from the east and they crossed
the English Channel and they invaded the
British Isles and destroyed the local
male population
and
procreated with the local females.
This invasion was the Yamna invasion
that ravaged rampaged across all of
Europe.
So the Celtic people are descendants of
of of that of that.
So you could say that the Kelts were not
exactly the original inhabitants of
England, but longtime inhabitants of of
of the British Isles. So the Celtic
people, they typically are characterized
historically by red hair or blonde hair
and blue eyes, that sort of thing. And
they were the natives of England when
the Romans arrived.
And the Romans did not have a very high
opinion of them because they were rather
easy to defeat apparently. So the Kelt
that is the Kelts in in the British
Isles, but you also had Kelts in Western
Europe. If you look at Iberia, if you if
you if you look at uh present day Spain,
if you look at present day western
France or the whole of France.
So all of that area,
transalpine gold, as Julius Caesar would
say, all of that was Celtic land. Even
the Swiss you could say, were were
closely related to the Celtic peoples.
red hair and pretty wild kind of
reputation at least.
So that is the Kelts. Now who are the
Brits? The Brits were also the original
inhabitants of Brit of of the British
Isles. So they were also Celtic people.
And in in in in England in Britain you
had multiple Celtic tribes. The picked
the picked pe the pictish people and
other people. The picss typically were
very highly heavily tattooed people
historically that sort of thing. So the
Britons and and there's a region of
France called Britany, the western
region of France.
That's uh the people of that region are
closely connected to the Celtic people
of the British islands.
So the the the Britons and the people of
Britany and the when I say Britons, I'm
talking about the original British
people of the British islands, not
today's Britain. So these are all
subsets of the Celtic people. The Celtic
people were this big ethnic group that
lived in Western Europe and the British
islands. Okay. Now, let's talk about the
Gauts, the Tutons, the Normans, and the
Franks. Let's begin with the Tutons.
The Tutons were a Scandinavian tribe.
What is Scandinavia? It is present day
Sweden, Denmark, Norway, that region.
Let's go to the map.
Uh here is map.
Here is map. Okay. So we're talking
about the Sweden, Denmark, Norway, that
region that is called Scandinavia. And
the Tutons were a Scandinavian tribe or
a North European tribe.
Um the Romans called them the Tutons
and uh the Romans came in conflict with
them at various points in time and that
sort of thing. So they were not a
Germanic tribe, they were a northern
European tribe. That's the Tutons. And
today all the Germanic people are called
the Tutonic peoples for some reason.
Even the English Tutonic people, well,
they I'm not sure if it's historically
accurate, but that's the connotation
that's that is used these days. But the
original Tutons were a northern European
tribe known to the Romans. So, we have
done the Kelts, we've done the Tutons,
we've done the Britons. Now, let's talk
about
the Goths.
The Goths.
Now the Goths were also a northern
European tribe
and they also came from the Scandinavian
region originally
but uh they after the demise I mean the
gods fought the Romans and they proved
to be very powerful adversaries
because
the fourth or fifth century the gods
sacked Rome. They besieged Rome. They
broke through the gates. They conquered
the city and they sacked it.
And who was the king? It was Allaric was
it? So there were two two flavors of the
gods. The Ostrogoths and the Vissigotss.
The Ostrogoths were the eastern gods and
the Visigots were the western gods. So
it is the Vigotss who conquered Rome.
Their king was Allaric, I believe. And
they conquered Rome. And it was a
humiliation for Rome. And eventually the
Goths went westwards and they
established a kingdom in Iberia which is
now called Spain. And that kingdom
lasted until it was defeated by the Mos,
the Arabs who came from North Africa and
conquered Spain. So the the Arabs, the
Mos, they defeated a visigothic kingdom
in Spain.
Okay. So that is the Goths. They were a
northern European people from
Scandinavia originally.
Okay. Now, let's talk about the Franks
and the Normans. First, let's do the
Franks. The Franks were a Germanic tribe
who lived around the Rin River. Let's
let's find the R the Rin River.
So, I know exactly where to look at the
R. Go to the north the northern part of
Switzerland and you will find the Rine
because it forms the boundary.
Oopsy daisy. Where is it? Zumat. Zumat.
zumat. Okay, now I see it. So somewhere
here you have the rhythand
and schwitz. So it's the boundary
between Germany and Switzerland. So so
this is the Ryan river. It's a pretty
major river in Europe. And uh the
Frankish people, they lived on the banks
of the of the Rine at some point in
time. They were Germanic originally and
then they moved westwards into what what
was then eventually called Frankia, the
land of the Franks and uh they built
Christian kingdoms there and they also
fought the the Moors eventually who had
conquered Iberia which is Spain. So they
fought uh the the Arabs, the Muslims.
And the greatest greatest of the
Frankish king was Carolus Magnus or
Charleammana.
Charalamya was a great uh well you could
say he's the greatest of the French
kings and he is the infamous well he he
launched the inf infamous northern
crusades which were crusades against
Europeans to destroy the native European
religion and impose Christianity. So
that's what makes him great. Charlemagne
Carlos Magnus. Pretty pretty brutal guy
but regarded as a very great man. Um so
he was the king of the Franks and his
kingdom was called Frankia and
eventually it was called France. So the
Franks were the ancestors of the French.
U lastly the Normans. Who are the
Normans? Well I have to go to the map
again. Long interesting story. So
Normans,
if you see the movie Saving Private
Ryan, you the opening scene is brutal,
isn't it? So those of you who have see
who have seen it, I mean, you see it
from a first person perspective as if
you are one of the guys, one of the
soldiers who's landing on the beaches of
France, right? D-Day 1944, whichever
year it was. So those were the beaches
of Normandy, okay? Western France,
northwestern France, Normandy.
Now, why is it called Normandy? Because
the Normans lived there. Who were the
Normans is the question, right?
Who are the Normans? So, long long ago,
I'm talking about the first millennium
AD. So, around 800, 900 AD. That period
was called the Viking age. The Vikings
suddenly discovered that they could
cross the North Sea
and that they could raid England.
And one of the first raids
in England by the Vikings. Let me try
and find the place. Can I find it?
One of the first raids
was here, Lindesfarn.
There used to be a monastery here
and u the Vikings well the monastery
somehow caught fire and the Vikings uh
they they rescued the treasures of the
monastery.
Okay. Well, they essentially killed the
monks and stole the treasures. There was
a castle here, monastery somewhere here.
There are ruins there and so on. So, one
of the first raids happened here. And
then once the Vikings dis beside, who
are the Vikings? There were people from
Denmark, Sweden, Norway, Scandinavian
people. So, once the Vikings discovered
that you could cross the North Sea, then
they started launching raid after raid
of England and England. England became
like, you know, besieged by the Vikings
and this continued for a couple of
hundred years. This was called the
Viking age.
And not only after England they they
turned their their sides to France and
they started attacking France and there
was this great this great warrior of the
Vikings his name was Rolo Rolo. So he
was very good at attacking France and he
came all the way to Paris. So the king
of the Franks gave him a deal. You know
you know what Rolo you you here you're
raiding France because you want our
lands our territories. Why don't you
stop raiding? I'll give you the land you
want. I'll give you a huge part of
northwestern France. I will make you the
duke of this region. You will be a king
in your own right, but you will have to
well acknowledge me as the over overlord
of all of France. But beyond doing that,
you are the king of the region. So, Rolo
said, "Okay, I'm happy to do that." and
and of course he will have to defend
France from the subsequent Viking
invaders which he was happy to do. But
the condition was that if Rolo accepts
then his people must convert to
Christianity and marry French women. So
you have to become French Frankish and
Rolo accepted. So Rolo became the first
duke of the region and because they were
from the north they were called northmen
or Normans.
And eventually this place became called
Normandy because of them northwest
France. And one of his one of his
descendants his great great grandson or
great-grandson whichever it was was
William. His name was William. And he
was an illegitimate child of his father.
And his father had to go and fight the
crusades in Ut which is the holy land.
So supposedly you know Jerusalem the
region. That's why he had to put his
illegitimate son illegitimate son as a
as a stand-in duke. And the father died
in the crusade. And that's why this
13-year-old boy, bastard boy, like they
used to say those days, he became the
duke. And he had a very tough time. But
around the age of 50, he he was very
very strong, you know, a very powerful
kingdom, duch dut duchy. And he crossed
the English Channel and invaded England
and he conquered England. So he went
from being called William the Bastard to
William the Conqueror and that's how
England came under Norman rule. So
that's the Normans.
Okay. So I think we've done all of them.
The Kelts, the Goths, the Tutons, the
Franks, the Brits, and the Normans. All
right.
Amisha says, "Why was Persian the
official language of the Mughal court
when they were Turks?" Well, that's a
good question. It's some It's a question
I've taken a few years ago, but why not
take it again? It's been a while. So,
yes, the the Muggals, the Muggals were
Turks, right? Uh Babber was a failed
Turk prince who escaped from who was
born in Andi John in Usbakistan present
day Usbakistan and uh he came to India
looking for some land to grab and
because of the circumstances in India at
the time he was able to establish a
small little kingdom there. Barber his
son was the incredibly incompetent
Humayun.
Okay. So Humayun was the second in in
the line. Baba was the first who
established what would eventually be
called the Muggal Empire and and Humayan
was the second. Hayan was incredibly
incompetent. He was an absolute loser
and very soon he found that his kingdom
was taken over by an Afghan by a native
who was not a Turk was was local whose
name was Sher Sha Sher Shasturi. So he
loses his father's throne and he is in
exile running around. His wife delivers
a child in the court in in the house of
a Rajput chieftain. The child's name was
Jalaludin later known as Akbar.
And eventually he has to go to Kabul. He
has to go to Kandahar and from there he
has to go to Persia because he's been
pursued by the by the forces of Shera
Suri.
So Hummayun had to take refuge in the
court of Tahasp Shah Tahamasp of Iran
and Shah Tahamas welcomed him with
hospitality and treated him kindly and
pretty well treated him like a king and
so on and humun there's this famous
painting of Humayun and Tahasp
u let let's let's let's find it right in
which Humayun is is showed as a
supplicant with his arms out like with
his hands out like this let's let's
quickly look at it okay very interesting
in very very good painting. Tamas and
Humayun
and
and uh Humayun.
All right, let's take a look at this
shahhatas and humayun. Take a look.
So, if I if I can make this larger,
give me a second.
Let's remove that and let's find
where isayun
let's go to the
as always Wikipedia is not a good source
of information not necessarily but let's
find this
there we have it let's let's enlarge
this so if you look at home's hands
You will see that they are in the
begging posture. Right? So, Humayun had
to go as a supplicant to the court of
Tamasp and Tamus Tamas said, "Okay, I'll
help you. I'll give you soldiers. I'll
give you men. I'll help you reconquer
the kingdom you lost, but uh you have to
do me a favor. You have to convert to
Shia Islam."
So, Humayon was Sunnid. the the
Persians, the Iranians were were Shia
and uh so Himayun was kind of coerced
forced into becoming Shia and then he
comes back to India and and the the the
the condition was Tamas imposed one
condition that I will help you reconquer
the land you lost, the kingdom you lost,
but you have to give me a Was it Hat?
Was it was it Kandahar? Was it Kabul? It
was not Kabul. it was probably Hat or or
Kandahar that part of his kingdom which
is now currently Afghanistan. So that
was a deal. So Hayun comes back with a
with an army given by Tamasp and slowly
he's able to reconquer uh parts of the
kingdom and then Sher Sasuri was
experimenting with gunpowder and and he
blew himself up. So he died a stupid
death and that would obviously have
helped my own lot and eventually he was
able to reconquer Dilli and sit in his
father's throne again. So then he finds
that he again has a kingdom but his
entire staff is Persian
and that's how Persian became the court
language of the Muggal court essentially
in brief. So he came with with a bunch
of you know officials and bureaucrats
and administrators and soldiers. So they
formed the nucleus of his new kingdom
and that's why everything was done in
Persian thereafter. And when he went to
Persia, Hummayan was like very very
impressed with all the Persian
architecture and all that. So he came
back with a very favorable impression of
of the Persian um culture and all that.
So he was happy to have Persian as the
court language. That's how it happened.
So before this the court language of the
muggles was Chagatai.
Prem says, "What led the Ottomans to
block trade routes from India to
Europe?"
Mhm.
What was his name? Muhammad II, Muhammad
the 1st, Muhammad the Conqueror. He's
the guy who does 185. Oh, sorry, what am
I saying? 15 No, 1453.
Once again, let's Google it. Muhammad
Muhammad the Muhammad the first
the conqueror. Muhammad the Was was he
first or second? He was the second
Muhammad. His father was was Barzed
Bahamaz. What was Bazid?
What was his father's name?
What was his daddy's name? Um, born is
dynasty father. Murad Murad II. Okay.
So, this is the guy Muhammad II. Okay.
Who conquered Constantinople
in 1453.
He was 21 at that time when he conquered
the city. It was called
what was it called? the the red apple
kizilma in Turkish.
So Constantinople used to be the capital
of the Byzantine Empire. It was called
Bzantion in the past but then emperor
Constantine reamed it after his own
after himself. So then it used to be it
came to be called Constantinople and it
was the seat of the Eastern Roman Empire
also known as the Byzantine Empire. Now
when in 1453 Constantinople finally fell
to the Turks by the time the Byzantine
Empire was was shrunk to to nothingness
only Constantinople and the surrounding
areas. So the biz so the Turk Empire was
already kind of there but after the fall
of Constantinople they took over very
rapidly uh whatever was left of what
used to be the Byzantine Empire.
So the Europeans
from Roman times were trading were
importing their favorite products from
India,
spices,
textiles, whatnot. And they used to and
in exchange they used to uh they used to
sell send gold to India. So India was
exporting spices and and textiles and
whatever else and the Romans were paying
India in gold and all of the trade was
happening by land.
Now if you look at the map you will see
what the deal is.
So when you're coming by land your
where is okay let's quickly go. So if
you're coming by land you will obviously
cross Constantinople because you don't
want to go all the way north of north
north of the Black Sea north of the
Caspian Sea into central Asia and then
come into India by crossing the
Himalayas. It's madness. It's better to
cross the Balkans,
cross from Constantinople, from Thrace
into Anatolia and then go straight via
via Mesopotamia and Persia into India.
As simple as that. Going via Central
Asia was difficult and challenging
because it was full of Turk tribes which
was a problem because they were very
hostile to the Europeans and uh there
was no sea route. There was no Sue canal
at the time and so on. So when the Turks
took over this great land bridge the the
straight of the Bosphorus in the entire
surrounding region the sea of Marmara
and uh Chanakal or the straight of the
Dardels then their land route to India
was blocked off. Now the question is why
did the Turks block the land route? Why
did they not allow the Europeans to
continue trade with India? I mean
if you are enemies why would you help
why would you allow that to continue?
The Turks wanted to conquer the whole of
Europe. Sulleman who is called Sullean
the Magnificent, he tried to conquer
Vienna and he was hammering on the gates
of Vienna. He besieged Vienna and well
things didn't turn out well well for
that siege. But you know the Turks were
the enemies of what they call
Christianom which is the European
kingdoms. So if Europe is trading with
India and the Indians are bloody Hindus
from their perspective, why would they
want that trade to continue? block it. I
think it should be so that's that's why.
Okay.
Okay. Krishna of the Surinamese
Netherlands says as we know the Veda
scriptures and traditions and the Avesta
scriptures and traditions are cont what
excuse me what
the Vic scriptures are contemporaneous
with the Avesta scriptures. We know we
don't know that. Okay. So there's lots
of misconceptions. I don't blame anybody
for having misconceptions
because these things aren't taught. The
Vedas are not contemporaneous with the
Avesta or or the the Persian uh
scriptures. They're not. Absolutely not.
Absolutely not.
The Persian language is an apranch
language. If you look at the the
Bhagastana inscription, Behon
inscription
and you read it, it's in the uniform
script. If you read it, it sounds like
slightly mangled Sanskrit. It's not pure
Sanskrit. It is corrupted Sanskrit. You
do you want me to do that? Let me do it.
Okay, let's let's go to Google.
I I'll read it for you. How about that?
Okay.
Bisun
inscription transliteration.
All right. Leuse whatever that is. Let
us read the first. Okay. This is okay.
This is the first part of the Bhagastana
incription.
He's describing his holiness. I think
you can understand what I'm saying here.
I think you can understand what I'm
saying. This is broken mangled Sanskrit.
This is not something that is
contemporaneous with a pure with a time
when pure Sanskrit was spoken. It is an
apa branch language. What is upper
brancher? It it means corruption.
What are Hindi, Bengali,
um Kashmiri, Marati, Gujarati,
Rajasthani, Punjabi, Haranvi. These are
aparent languages. These are corrupted
languages that have descended from
Sanskrit. They no longer have the purity
of Sanskrit. We don't say we say machi.
We don't say matsia.
We say hat. We don't say husta. We say
ak. We don't say chakshu. The purity is
gone. The languages have degraded.
Similarly, if you read that, it is
slightly degraded Sanskrit
which means it is a descendant language
of Sanskrit. cannot in any
way be be contemporaneous with the
rigid. Impossible.
The Persians were descendants of ancient
Indians. They were called the Parhua
people. The Parhua were one of the clans
that were on the losing side in the
battle of the 10 kings.
They went westwards and they settled
down in what the land that is now
bearing their name Persia. So the Veda
scriptures are not contemporaneous with
the Avesta scriptures. Absolutely not.
The Veda scriptures came long long
before the Avesta. Okay. First of all,
let's let's establish that
um and there are also persons who are
mentioned in both the Veda scriptures
and Avesa scriptures. Yeah, of course.
Of course.
So if you are a descendant of of an old
lineage, you will have the memory. You
will mention those lineages and all. I
mean look what Da says. He's saying that
my daddy was was what's he saying? My my
daddy was Vistaspa. Vishtaspa. My
Vishtaspa's father was Arsamya.
His father was was
Vishtaspa then Arsamaya then Arya Ramna
then Chishpish then Hakamanish.
He's establishing his lineage. And if
you if you read if you read the shahama
the shahame well the shahame was written
at a very very difficult time when
Persia was conquered by the by the
Arabs.
I think it was Gori or Gnavi who had who
had commissioned the shaame. I always
get confused about Gori and Gnavi who
came first. Please forgive me. You can
always look up who came first. It was
one of those two barbarians who had
commissioned Ferdosi to write the
Shahame
and the Shaame is not very it doesn't
have present a very flattering portrait
of the Arabs by the way. Okay. Um now if
you look at the Shaame I will not open
the Shaame and read it out for you but
if you look at the origin of the Persian
people in the Shaame it essentially is
the same origin
story that you have in the Rigveda. So
obviously you will have if you are the
same part of the same lineage and same
traditions deep back in time you will
remember the past and your scriptures
will reference the same people who are
referencing the older scriptures. So no
surprise there but let us not for one
moment believe that the Persian uh Astan
scriptures were contemporaneous with the
Vedas. Absolutely not. What are we
talking about? The Aistan script
scriptures aroroastrian
scriptures. Zaratustra
he lived around 600 BC after he lived he
said to have lived after the rule of
hakamanish or akamanish the founder of
the kirit dynasty.
So, Zoroastrinism came became a force in
Persia sometime later after the founding
of the uh of the cabinet dynasty. What
does it tell you? What question does it
raise in your mind if you are
intelligent and a thinking person? The
question you will ask yourself is
what religion did Hakkamish practice?
the founder of the dynasty
they would have practiced Hinduism
right okay
123 says what are the markers of
civilizational continuity is it language
is it religion is it culture is it
ethnicity India has held on strongly to
Hinduism and Hindu Hindu culture to this
day but Sanskrit is no longer the lingua
frana so to say and much of the period
between the Indus Valley civilization
and Indian empires that we know of has
been forgotten. It's been lost. Yes. Uh
China likes to boast about likes to
boast about a 5,000-y old civilization
despite having spent entire dynasties
ruled by conquerors. So have we. Uh as
well as erasing much of their own
religion and culture in the name of
communism. Yeah, they have done that.
And we have done that in the name of
secularism. Uh some in the west like to
see themselves as inheritors of the
Roman Empire despite having abandoned
their pantheon to carry the torch of a
Middle Eastern god. That's true. who
today can truly claim to be the
continuation of an ancient civilization.
You are raising very well actually very
important questions. The questions you
are raising force
force one
to think from first principles. What's
it mean to think from first principles?
What does it mean? It means you to ask
yourself fundamental questions. What is
a civilization? You have to clarify the
concept in your mind before you can
answer this question. What is a
civilization?
What are the characteristics of a
civilization? We use the term very
vaguely, very randomly like some
abstract concept civilization. Another
is national interest. Do you even know
what the national interest is? But we're
talking about civilization here. So what
is a civilization? Does a civilization
have any characteristic? Can you
actually define what a civilization is?
Can you? That's the big question. Well,
you can and you should be able to do
that. So, what's a civilization? First
of all, a civilization is an advanced
society.
It's an advanced society. It has a
number of characteristics. What are
these characteristics? First of all, it
in a civilization, you have a highly
evolved and institutionalized
indigenous culture.
highly evolved culture and it should be
institutionalized. Your institutions
should be embedded in the value or the
or your cultural values should be
embedded in your institutions. Ask
yourself is that the case for India? Is
your constitution grounded in India's
culture and civilization? Are your laws
grounded in India's culture and
civilization? Are your institutions
grounded in India's laws and
civilizations?
Your law, your constitution, your inst
institutions must be based in the
indigenous culture and the indigenous
values and morality.
That's one. Secondly, you need an
indigenous system of governance, not
something that somebody gave to you as a
gift from outside. Then you need a
highly organized and harmonious society.
You need a high degree of social and
political stability. You need a single
civilizational language.
You need a large geographical area. A
small little thing cannot be a
civilization. You need a large
geographical area. You need a powerful
economy. You need high levels of
prosperity.
And you need a large sphere of economic,
military, and cultural influence that
extends well beyond your borders.
Then a civilization has it has its own
script of writing. It doesn't use
foreign scripts or imported scripts. It
uses its own scripts. A civilization has
its own calendar and its own system of
timekeeping. And finally, a civilization
is a net exporter of culture, not a net
net importer of culture. Now ask
yourself, does India fit the bill?
Does it
is India civilization today?
I think I will I will leave it as a
question instead of answering the
question. I I want some of you to think
sometimes
ask yourselves
is India can India actually be
classified as a civilization today?
China can China be classified? Who can
be classified as a civilization? Is this
the age of civilizations or is is this
the age of empires
and Vasalhood or something else? I I
would like you to let me know in the
comments.
Amisha says, "Did did women in early Vic
period enjoy greater freedom than
medieval India?" I'm not sure what the
medieval period is. How do you define
the medieval period? But let's say it's
the past 1,000 years. Okay, medieval
means middle ages. Well, the European
concept of medieval is is is something
that is can only fit Europe. For us,
let's say the medieval period is the
period after 10,000 AD. after 1000 AD
when India was slowly gradually coming
under siege and uh being attacked by
foreigners and slowly gradually being
occupied bit by bit
well under the foreigners were Turks.
Did women have any freedom? Are we are
we kidding ourselves? Women had to cover
themselves and they they had to stay
indoors. Women had to disappear from
society from public society from public
life. What freedom? There was no
freedom.
Compare it to the Vic period. I mean
women wrote the many of the verses of
the rigveda
that's freedom show me any
any religion any any religion one show
me one religion in the world in which
when it comes to the foundational sacred
text the central central most sacred
text show me a religion where one word
has been written by a woman
there you have it
Krishna Krishna of the Surinamese
Netherlands says these days English is
the world language what was the world's
well global language or whatever um in
ancient times so more than
around 600 CE to 300 BC 3,000 BC beyond
that what world language was used in
both paratra Persia Mesopotamia ancient
Egypt Phoenicia and so on interesting
question so today because of uh modern
technology ology the world is
interconnected
and that's why you need a a link
language and because of the domination
of the Anglo-Saxons in the past 500
years that link language or global
language international language is is
English before it used to be French
because the French had conquered England
the Normans it used to be French so for
a long time French was considered to be
the language of diplomacy today if you
if you meet Indian diplomats you'll find
that they speak some some form of French
some speak good French, excellent
French, some speak some French, but all
of them well it's it's prestigious to
speak French because it is the language
of diplomacy. You will see Mr.
Shashitaur speaking in French with the
the Russian envoys and so on. So French
used to be the language of diplomacy. It
still is kind of and English is the
global language. Now if you go back to
300 AD or CE, the world was not
interconnected.
It wasn't
kings would never meet.
If you were kings from the Indian
subcontinent, you may meet sometimes
under special circumstances. But if you
were a king from India, you would not
meet a king from Persia or you would not
meet a king from Egypt or a king from
South America or a king from Europe. It
never ever happened.
Never.
And that's why there was no world
language
in Asia. There was a civilizational
language which was Sanskrit because
Indians had spread far and wide and much
of Asia was Indianized as we know. So if
Indian merchants went to Shri Vijaya or
Majapahit
well they could speak Sanskrit and they
would be understood at least by the
nobility and those who mattered. If
Indians went to China to the court of
the Tang emperor they could speak in in
Sanskrit and they would be understood
because you would have scholars there
who spoke Sanskrit. Even if Indians went
to Japan or Korea coro ko goryo they
could speak Sanskrit and be understood
by the by the powers that be.
So in Asia you had Sanskrit.
Um if you went to Tibet you could speak
speak and so also in Mongolia
eventually. U Persia as long as Persia
was free not conquered by the Arabs you
could speak speak Sanskrit there and you
would be understood beyond that did not
really work. So it's a huge domain, huge
geographical area where Sanskrit was the
link language, the civilizational
language but there was no global
language as such in but there were
hegemonic languages in Europe for
example Latin was spoken across Europe
because the Rome Romans had conquered
much of Europe most of Europe and they
had imposed their language everywhere.
So in Europe for the longest time Latin
was the link language. It eventually
became the language of the the the
Vatican Empire.
So you had Latin there over a certain
amount of geographical area and in Asia
over a much vaster geographical area you
had Sanskrit and uh that's about how it
was Africa we have no idea because their
history has been destroyed it's been
erased so we don't know in the Americas
once again their history was destroyed
they were conquered and and smashed so
we don't know about that also so I can
tell you about Europe and India and and
Asia
Jajnulka says do you think this Labor by
Valini Zumpiri, Shawi, MJ, etc. The
Persian Plateau served as a hub for homo
sapiens after the main out of Africa
dispersal nature communications 2024 and
its supplements. Do you think this paper
and its supplements are accurate in
their conclusions about the history of
homo sapiens? So I took I took a look at
the paper before I selected this
question
and the and the paper essentially
concludes it says what are the main
claims of the paper? It says that we
know the Afric we know that the out of
Africa migration happened sometime
around 70 80,000 years before today
around that time 70 80 85 maybe whatever
and the paper claims that the main bulk
of the population that came out of
Africa it settled in Persia
and it's it it remained in Persia for 20
30,000 years and it intermingled
intermixed with the Neanderthals that's
why you have human that's why you have
Neanderthal DNA in in us because we are
the ancestors we are the descendants of
those unions and after 30 40 20 30,000
years from Persia there was a dispersal
of homo sapiens across Eurasia. That's
what the paper says.
Now
how
is is is the paper accurate is what
you're asking.
Look next to Persia there is a gigantic
subcontinent that is super fertile.
So doesn't it make more sense for humans
to go and settle there? Persia is dry
and arid. I mean look at Persia. Persia
is dry and arid those days around the
out of Africa migration. There was more
greenery around the this the coastlines
of the sea the the the the the seashore
but the Persian plateau the overall bulk
of of Persia overall it was arid. It was
dry. Why would anyone settle there?
That's one that's one issue with the
paper. Second, and instead of making a
claim,
instead of making a claim, let me show
you.
Okay, there's another issue. You see,
let me Google this. Let us find it on
Google. Okay, did
ancient Indians. Okay, first of all, not
not this. Okay, before I even go here,
let me show you something else. Let's go
to the maps first. Okay,
here is map. Yes. Now let's Google Lake
Toba.
Lake Toba. And it's going to zoom in to
Sumatra. Zoom out. You will find that
you are in Sumatra. Zoom in. You will
find this this big lake here. Nice
pretty lake. And there's this island on
the lake. Okay. And if you uh
and if you put the satellite images on,
nice pretty place. It's like a tourist
destination. And you will find that
there are resorts and waterfront cities
and 4.6 stars and all that. But this
lake is the extinct caldera of a
gigantic super volcano. And this super
volcano explosion last happened about
80,000 years ago. Okay. One of the
largest super volcano explosions ever of
all time. That was the Toba eruption of
about 70,000 years ago.
Now why am I talking about this? Because
I want to show you something else. So
now you have in in your mind the Toba
super volcano explosion. Now let's go to
Google.
All right.
Did ancient
Indians
survive Toba
eruption?
Did ancient Yes. Ancient humans in India
survived the Toba super volcano eruption
about 74,000 years ago. Archaeological
evidence from the Dhaba site and the Son
Valley River showing continuous human
occupation before and after the event
and you have the these all these
articles you know the scientific
research papers that that show you that.
Okay, you can Google it in your own free
time. My point is that 74,000 years ago
India ancient humans were living in
India before and after the Toba super
volcano eruption event.
Who are they?
They were homo sapiens. Yes. So homo
sapiens were living in India and India
is a kind of subcontinent which will
which can sustain a gigantic population
of homo sapiens compared to Persia. So
there are multiple issues with this
paper is all I would say. I'm sure if
you look at the paper in isolation it's
well written and you know conclusions
may be well rigorous scientifically
valid but if you broaden the scope of
the paper then you will see issues. If
you just focus on the narrow Persia
region, it may make sense.
Okay, what else do we have? Um, okay,
let's take one more question. User Prem
says, "My question is that what was the
indigenous script of Indonesia and the
language of Australia before
colonization? How influenced were these
languages by Indian languages, culture
scripts before colonial impact?" Right?
See, Indonesia was never colonized.
India was colonized by the first the
Turks and then the British, the
Europeans. Indonesia was not colonized
but it was eventually there was a
conversion to Islam from Hinduism. Now
Australia was colonized about I don't
know 200 years ago 250 years ago by the
by the pirates of the British Navy of of
the British Empire pirates. And yeah
before before that did the Australians
have a script? I the the indigenous
Australians or the aboriginal
Australians did they have a script? As
far as I know, they did not have a
script of writing. But the Indonesians,
of course, they had scripts. They had
multiple scripts. So, uh let's once
again go to Google and there are
multiple scripts. Uh
Sunda script
script. Is it Sunda or Sundan?
Sundani script. So, if you look at the
script, you will see that it is a script
uh and it was derived from Brahi.
Okay. And they claimed that Brahimi came
from Aramaic and Phoenician and all that
which is utter nonsense but whatever. Uh
so it was called axara sununda
and this is what it was like kaka kaka
kaga chaja and all that. This was the
sundan script. You also have other
scripts balin
uh sorry balin script. So you have a
balin script. Once again this will be
derived from here we have it from brahi.
Okay. So you have the brahi the balindi
script ka ka ga
ha and so on that is the balini script
what other Indonesian scripts do you
have Indonesian scripts
category the batak script bond script so
you have javani script is also right
javani script and so on so you had all
these brahi derived scripts that were
used in Indonesia and that's obviously
because of the Indian influence uh in in
the region. So yeah, definite Indian
influence. No question about that.
Okay. Now, okay, we have crossed two
hours. So I still have more questions.
But I'll stop it for today. But I will
take some questions from the live chat.
So if you have questions, I'll I'll I'll
spend 10 minutes on the live chat taking
questions. Right? So go for it. Ask your
questions and I'll take a few.
Do we have any questions?
Uh I'm not sure I have the answer to
this question. Did when did mirror usage
begin in ancient India and how did this
compare with early mirrors elsewhere
like volcanic glass? I I don't know
about this. Uh I have not done any any
research on the usage of mirrors in
ancient India. So I am afraid I would
not be able to answer the question. Now
we have super chats. Good god. Uh today
is not a super chat session. So please
please don't don't take any more super
chats but I will whatever is there I
I'll I'll take it. Uh Sum says what was
the name of Bat before Bat. It was
always Batwash. It was also called Aryat
the land of the Arya people. That's us
and Bat because of our great ancient
ancestor King Barat right. Uh
yeah so that is the ancient name of
Barat. Um
unknown says I'm interested in
researching the history of the land
Jammu where I was born. Where should I
start? I completed my student school
this year. Uh once again I am not by any
stretch of the imag imagination any kind
of expert in the history of the region
Jammu. Uh you would have to look at look
into local records. Dogra Dogra records.
Um you should look at the the the the
chronicles the Raja Tarangiri of
Kalhana. So I would say yeah start from
the Raja Tarangini of Kalhana who Kalhan
was was a writer he was a historian who
wrote a history of of Kashmir in the
overall region the surrounding region
about a thousand years before today
about thousand years ago and you can
also look up the records of the of the
Dala kings wherever they are available
so that's where you could start perhaps
I don't know of any books that have been
written about Jamu so can't tell sorry
okay Valika says I wonder how the
British held power for 200 years to what
extent did Indians themselves working
The spies or agents make this possible.
Do we have historical records of such
collaboration?
The British were able to hold power
because India was divided. First of all,
when a land is divided against itself,
it's very easy for for outsiders to take
advantage of that. There are so many
examples in history of of this divide
and conquer, divide and rule strategy.
So that's number one. India was not
united.
Well, and the British were able to see
some somebody may give give a
counterpoint. We had the Marata Empire
which had unified the whole of India and
and restored Hindus for Hindi raashtra
Hindi Hindvi right true
but why did the Marata empire
disintegrate
because of in political infighting it
was divided against itself eventually
and the British took advantage of that
so the British did not liberate India
from the muggles they destroyed defeated
the Marata Empire because the Marata
Empire was in the stage of infighting
uh Indians working as spies and yeah
look whenever a land is under occupation
you will find all these nefarious
elements wherever it is whether it's
India whether it is any other land under
occupation who will work for the
foreigners you saw the same pattern over
and over again in North America and
South America
when the Spanish arrived yeah I mean who
conquered the Aztec triple alliance
Cortez why was he able to conquer the
Aztec triple alliance in 1519 1520 1521.
How? First of all, because of smallpox
that the uh local inhabitants were not
had never been exposed to which which
made them die out in the millions. And
secondly because a lot of people a lot
of the surrounding kingdoms who had
grievances against the Aztec Empire they
took they they fought on the side of the
of the invaders the Spaniards Han Cortez
Han Cortez and his concistadors that's
why the triple alliance went down the
Aztec Empire without the collaboration
of the natives who thought oh these
people have come from god knows what
what far away places so they'll go away
so let's take their help and defeat the
Aztec tribal alliance finished
again when it comes to the Inca Empire.
So this time it's in South America, the
western part of South America, the Andes
mountains. You have Franchesco Pedar,
another barbarian who came from Spain
who destroyed the Inca Empire. 1530s
he he defeated the Inca Emperor
Atawalpa. How did this happen? Once
again collaboration.
Whenever a land is under foreign
occupation, you will find all these
termites cropping up.
So yeah, Indians also you'll you'll have
people who work for the British.
Eventually the system became such that
you had to work for the British
otherwise you'll starve to death. The
British imposed a foreign education
system upon India and they destroyed all
India's native industries and all the
jobs that were only the only jobs that
were then available were government jobs
working for the godamned British. So you
had to work for them. They created the
conditions such that there was no other
opportunity. There was no other option
for Indians
and uh there are other more more
nefarious examples of collaboration and
I will not go into those details because
it will be super controversial. There
are very prominent figures like like
prominent prominent who are British
collaborators. Can anybody
guess or or venture some names who those
very high ranking super prominent
British collaborators were were?
Do do we have some names? I I am not
saying anything. I have I've had enough
controversies.
I Let's see.
I see people saying something.
Oh, good god. Good god. I am not saying
anything. Okay. I' I've had enough
controversies. I'm not I'm not quoting
more controversies now.
All right. Magnificent leaders, right?
Okay.
Uh
yeah. Okay. Very interesting names
coming out. Okay. We will take one last
question. The Shir Geopolitical Dubai
from Indor. Why did Joseph Stalin
dislike the magnificent Shir Neu? did
have a relationship with the USSR start
improving about after the death of
Stalin. I don't know if he disliked Neu.
I am sure he did not have a very high
regard for the magnificent Mr. Nu which
is very naughty Mr. Salin very naughty.
See I I'm I'm I hear that there was this
incident where you know uh Stalin was
meeting with the Indian ambassador of
the time to Moscow and they were
discussing a map of India for some
reason and Stalin is pointing to this
little island. and he's saying what is
this island called? So the Indian
ambassador says that that's that's not
India that is Sri Lanka
it's a separate country and Stalin asks
him why
and obviously if you so you can imagine
the kind of that he would not have a
great amount of respect for Mr. narrow
because why what the hell are you people
doing? Are you people idiots essentially
is what he was asking.
So um maybe there was the extent of
dislike beyond that Mr. Nehu worshiped
the USSR but he did not implement the
USSR's reforms in India the mass
industrialization the industrial monster
base that the USSR created to turn into
a superpower. Mr. did not replicate
that. Instead, he did Fabian socialism
gently, gently never happening, right?
Uh,
okay. What else do we have?
Anything interesting?
Nikkesh Dahal says, "Why do many Indians
foreignize Nepal? How many lands do we
have to lose? Do you consider Nepal as
foreign? Aren't all Nepal is Indians?
India map looks like a piece is carved
out of top. I don't know which India is
foreignized Nepal. I don't see Nepal as
a foreign land. It's obviously a
separate sovereign country and we
respect that. But the Nepales are our
people. What the hell? I mean
which which nationality has the
privilege to serve in the Indian army?
If if Nepali citizens can serve in the
Indian army, it it shows how much we
trust the people of Nepal. You will
never allow foreigners to serve in your
armed forces. Right? If there are some
Indians who have this stupid attitude
will I what can I say? Every country has
its share of idiots, doesn't it?
That's what I would say. I I don't
consider Nepal to be a foreign country.
We are the same people. So if if this
this is what you have experienced, I I
I'm sorry that that's the case, you
know. But I I personally do not see
Nepal as a foreign land at all. We are
all the same people. We have the same
blood, same origins, same shared
history, culture, civilization,
everything. That's how I see it, sir.
That's how I see it. Nikesh G.
Okay. Um I I I don't know about any any
updates update about the Salei Chariots.
Uh I I don't know. I' I've not seen
anything in the news recently and I've
not been uh looking into this. So I'm
not sure. Are they from the Mahabharat
era and horse? Look, they're from
whatever time period. We don't quite
know what was the time period of the
Mahabharat. Once we have a definitive
dating of the Mahabharat, then we can
compare the date of the Mahabharat with
the date carbon dating of the tali
chariots. Right now we can't say so what
is the age of the tali chariots? Maybe
3,000 4,000 whatever thousand years. But
until we have a clear understanding of
when did the Mahabarat happen?
Let's say 5,000 years ago. Let's say
4,000 years ago. Whenever it is until we
know that how can we compare? So I don't
know, right? I don't know.
Latangi Sur says, "Please give a home
vlog home tour vlog and also bookshelf
tour vlog." Um,
see I am doing this live streams every
day when I'm spending eight hours doing
work, right? Writing. So now onwards
from last episode onwards for the first
15 minutes of that live stream I am
pulling out a bunch of books like five
six books and I am speaking about those
books. So, so that's the way I'm going
to do the the bookshelf tour. Not by
going to the actual bookshelf with this
camera. And here we are. Here we go. You
know, zooming it and zing zooming it
out, whatever, but by bringing the books
here to to where I'm doing that live
stream from. And every episode, the
first 15 minutes or so, I will do a
review of a number of books. I I promise
you, I have so many books. This this
will go on for a while. So, yeah.
All right.
Uh, one second. A whole inscription says
Mahabharat was 3102 BC. It it does say
that. So that's a very strong piece of
evidence of of a date there. Yeah. But
you would need to corrobor corroborate
that corroborate that with some kind of
archaeological evidence. So my question
is why isn't
why isn't the archaeological survey of
India excavating Indra Prasta which is
in the capital city of India? What is
stopping them?
Anyway, yeah. Okay, we are done for the
day. Thank you so much for all the
questions. I'm going to end it here. 2
hours 15 minutes pretty robust amount of
time. So thank you so much everybody.
Once again, I'm ending ending the live
stream here and then tomorrow we're
going to have a super chat live stream
all about geopolitics. Thank you so
much. Take care everybody. Keep asking
questions. Keep raising your standards.
Keep working hard. Do extremely well and
I will see you in tomorrow's live
stream. Thank you Shubaratri. Good
night. Good day wherever you are. Take
care. Bye.